<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sheikh Imtiaz Ahmed</title>
    <description>Polyglot Programmer, Computer Scientist, Enterprise and Cloud Software Engineer.
</description>
    <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sheikhimtiaz.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 16:59:14 +0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 16:59:14 +0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Unraveling the Actor Model</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the realm of concurrent computing, the Actor Model stands as a pivotal paradigm, offering a unique approach to designing and implementing distributed systems. Originating from foundational work in the 1970s, particularly through the efforts of Carl Hewitt, the Actor Model has evolved significantly, influencing languages, frameworks, and systems across diverse domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-genesis-of-the-actor-model&quot;&gt;The Genesis of the Actor Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Actor Model finds its roots in the pioneering work of Carl Hewitt, Peter Bishop, and Richard Steiger, who introduced it in a seminal paper titled “A Universal Modular ACTOR Formalism for Artificial Intelligence” in 1973. This model was conceived as a theoretical framework for representing concurrent computation, wherein computational entities, known as actors, interact through asynchronous message passing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-the-actor-model&quot;&gt;Understanding the Actor Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, the Actor Model revolves around the concept of actors, which are autonomous, encapsulated units of computation that communicate exclusively via message passing. Each actor maintains its state and can spawn new actors, enabling the construction of highly scalable and fault-tolerant systems. Unlike traditional concurrency models, such as threads and locks, the Actor Model inherently avoids issues like deadlock and race conditions through its message-driven nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pioneering-works-alan-kay-and-joe-armstrong&quot;&gt;Pioneering Works: Alan Kay and Joe Armstrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Kay’s Smalltalk language, developed in the 1970s, embodied the principles of the Actor Model, albeit in a different guise. Smalltalk’s objects, akin to actors, communicated through message passing, laying the foundation for modern object-oriented programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Armstrong, along with his colleagues, introduced the Erlang programming language in the late 1980s, heavily influenced by the Actor Model. Erlang’s lightweight processes, known as “actors,” coupled with its built-in support for message passing and fault tolerance, made it an ideal choice for building robust and highly concurrent systems, particularly in telecommunications and distributed computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-state-and-industry-leading-solutions&quot;&gt;Current State and Industry Leading Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the Actor Model continues to thrive, with numerous implementations and frameworks tailored to different programming languages and environments. Akka, a popular Actor Model implementation for the Java Virtual Machine (JVM), provides developers with a powerful toolkit for building scalable and resilient systems. Microsoft’s Orleans framework offers a similar approach in the .NET ecosystem, simplifying the development of distributed applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-cases-and-applications&quot;&gt;Use Cases and Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Actor Model finds application across a spectrum of domains, ranging from distributed systems and cloud computing to IoT (Internet of Things) and gaming. In distributed systems, actors enable the creation of highly responsive and fault-tolerant microservices architectures. In gaming, the Actor Model facilitates real-time interactions and dynamic world simulations. Similarly, in IoT, actors can represent physical devices, orchestrating communication and data processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-prospects-and-active-research-areas&quot;&gt;Future Prospects and Active Research Areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, the Actor Model holds promise for addressing the challenges of modern computing paradigms, including edge computing, serverless architectures, and decentralized systems. Active research areas include optimizing actor runtime systems for performance and scalability, exploring novel actor-based programming languages, and integrating the Actor Model with emerging technologies such as blockchain and quantum computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the Actor Model stands as a testament to the enduring quest for more efficient and reliable concurrent computation. From its humble beginnings to its pervasive influence in contemporary software engineering, the Actor Model continues to inspire innovation and shape the landscape of distributed computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hewitt, C., Bishop, P., &amp;amp; Steiger, R. (1973). A Universal Modular ACTOR Formalism for Artificial Intelligence. IJCAI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Armstrong, J. (2003). Making reliable distributed systems in the presence of software errors. ACM.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agha, G. (1986). Actors: A Model of Concurrent Computation in Distributed Systems. MIT Press.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Akka Documentation: https://akka.io/docs/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Orleans Documentation: https://dotnet.github.io/orleans/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hewitt, C. (2015). The Actor Model (everything you wanted to know, but were afraid to ask). MIT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 06:00:01 +0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/cstheory/2022/04/10/actor-model.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sheikhimtiaz.me/cstheory/2022/04/10/actor-model.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cstheory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Gayeebi Lang: Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I will share my understanding on the following topics in this series -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined Object-Lambda Architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GraalVM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Truffle Language Implementation API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-combined-object-lambda-architecture-cola&quot;&gt;Understanding Combined Object-Lambda Architecture (COLA)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Combined Object-Lambda Architecture (COLA) is a modern architectural pattern that blends the strengths of both the Object-Oriented Programming (OOP) paradigm and the Lambda Architecture. It aims to provide a unified approach for building scalable, maintainable, and efficient distributed systems, particularly in the context of big data processing and real-time analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;object-oriented-programming-oop&quot;&gt;Object-Oriented Programming (OOP)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OOP is a programming paradigm centered around the concept of “objects,” which encapsulate data and behavior. OOP promotes modularity, reusability, and extensibility through features such as encapsulation, inheritance, and polymorphism. However, traditional OOP paradigms may struggle with distributed systems’ challenges, such as scalability and fault tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lambda-architecture&quot;&gt;Lambda Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lambda Architecture is a design pattern for building large-scale, distributed systems that process both batch and real-time data streams. It comprises three layers: the batch layer, serving as a system of record for historical data processing; the speed layer, handling real-time data processing and analytics; and the serving layer, which combines results from both layers to provide queryable views to users. While effective, implementing and maintaining a Lambda Architecture can be complex and require managing multiple technologies and codebases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-principles-of-combined-object-lambda-architecture-cola&quot;&gt;Key Principles of Combined Object-Lambda Architecture (COLA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unified Data Model:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA promotes a unified data model that spans both batch and real-time processing. This model encapsulates the core entities and relationships within the system, facilitating consistency and coherence across different processing layers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Object-Oriented Design:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA leverages OOP principles to design the core components and logic of the system. Objects represent real-world entities and encapsulate both data and behavior. This design promotes modularity, encapsulation, and code reuse, making the system easier to understand and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lambda Architecture Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA integrates the concepts of the Lambda Architecture to handle both batch and real-time data processing seamlessly. It leverages technologies such as Apache Spark for batch processing and Apache Flink or Apache Kafka Streams for real-time stream processing. By combining batch and stream processing, COLA enables comprehensive data analysis and insights generation across different time scales.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalability and Fault Tolerance:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA inherits the scalability and fault tolerance benefits of the Lambda Architecture. It can scale horizontally to handle increasing data volumes and accommodate growing user demands. Additionally, COLA incorporates fault tolerance mechanisms to ensure system resilience and reliability, such as data replication, checkpointing, and recovery strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexibility and Extensibility:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA emphasizes flexibility and extensibility in system design. It allows developers to adapt the architecture to evolving requirements and integrate new technologies or data sources seamlessly. This flexibility enables COLA-based systems to stay agile and responsive to changing business needs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits-of-combined-object-lambda-architecture-cola&quot;&gt;Benefits of Combined Object-Lambda Architecture (COLA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unified Development Paradigm:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA provides a unified development paradigm that combines the strengths of OOP and the Lambda Architecture, streamlining the development process and reducing complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalability and Performance:&lt;/strong&gt; By leveraging distributed processing frameworks for both batch and real-time data, COLA enables scalable and high-performance data processing, catering to large-scale data volumes and real-time analytics requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintainability and Understandability:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA’s object-oriented design promotes maintainability and understandability by encapsulating complexity within modular components and fostering code reuse and abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive Data Insights:&lt;/strong&gt; COLA facilitates comprehensive data insights by integrating batch and real-time processing seamlessly, enabling organizations to derive actionable insights from historical and real-time data sources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the Combined Object-Lambda Architecture (COLA) offers a cohesive and scalable approach to building distributed systems for big data processing and real-time analytics, bridging the worlds of object-oriented programming and the Lambda Architecture. By embracing unified data models, OOP principles, and distributed processing technologies, COLA empowers organizations to derive valuable insights and drive informed decision-making from diverse data sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-graalvm&quot;&gt;Understanding GraalVM&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM is a high-performance runtime that provides support for multiple programming languages and execution modes. Developed by Oracle Labs, GraalVM offers a polyglot runtime environment that allows developers to run applications written in different languages, including Java, JavaScript, Python, Ruby, and more, on a single virtual machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features-of-graalvm&quot;&gt;Features of GraalVM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;polyglot-execution&quot;&gt;Polyglot Execution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM supports polyglot execution, allowing developers to seamlessly interoperate between different programming languages within the same application. This capability enables developers to choose the best language for each component of their application, improving productivity and code maintainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-performance&quot;&gt;High Performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM boasts high-performance execution for both Just-In-Time (JIT) compiled code and Ahead-Of-Time (AOT) compiled code. Its optimizing compiler technology optimizes code across different languages, resulting in faster execution speeds and reduced memory overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;native-image-generation&quot;&gt;Native Image Generation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key features of GraalVM is its ability to generate native images from JVM-based applications. Native images are standalone executables that do not require a JVM for execution, resulting in faster startup times and reduced memory consumption. This feature is particularly beneficial for deploying applications in resource-constrained environments, such as serverless computing platforms and containerized environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;language-support&quot;&gt;Language Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM supports a wide range of programming languages, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript (including Node.js)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruby&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;R&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C/C++&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LLVM-based languages (such as Rust and Go)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This broad language support enables developers to leverage existing codebases and libraries written in different languages, fostering code reuse and interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-cases-of-graalvm&quot;&gt;Use Cases of GraalVM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;microservices-architecture&quot;&gt;Microservices Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM is well-suited for microservices architectures, where developers often use multiple programming languages and frameworks to build modular and scalable applications. By providing polyglot support and native image generation, GraalVM simplifies the development and deployment of microservices, leading to improved performance and resource utilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloud-native-applications&quot;&gt;Cloud-Native Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM’s native image generation feature makes it an ideal choice for building cloud-native applications that require fast startup times and low memory footprint. By creating lightweight, standalone executables, GraalVM enables developers to deploy applications more efficiently in cloud environments, resulting in improved scalability and cost-effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;performance-optimization&quot;&gt;Performance Optimization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraalVM’s optimizing compiler technology and support for AOT compilation help developers optimize the performance of their applications across different languages. By generating highly optimized native code, GraalVM improves application responsiveness and throughput, making it suitable for latency-sensitive and high-throughput workloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-directions-and-community-involvement&quot;&gt;Future Directions and Community Involvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GraalVM project continues to evolve through active community involvement and contributions. Future developments may include enhancements to language support, performance optimizations, and integration with emerging technologies and frameworks. Developers are encouraged to participate in the GraalVM community to shape the future direction of the project and contribute to its success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, GraalVM is a versatile runtime environment that offers polyglot execution, high performance, and native image generation capabilities. By supporting multiple programming languages and execution modes, GraalVM empowers developers to build efficient, scalable, and interoperable applications for a wide range of use cases and environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-truffle-language-implementation-api&quot;&gt;Understanding Truffle Language Implementation API&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Truffle Language Implementation API (LIA) is a framework that provides developers with tools and utilities for building custom programming languages on the Ethereum blockchain. Developed as part of the Truffle Suite, a popular development framework for Ethereum dApps (decentralized applications), the Truffle LIA simplifies the process of creating and deploying domain-specific languages (DSLs) tailored to smart contract development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview-of-truffle-language-implementation-api-lia&quot;&gt;Overview of Truffle Language Implementation API (LIA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truffle LIA offers a comprehensive set of features and functionalities to facilitate the development of DSLs for Ethereum smart contracts. It provides abstractions and utilities for defining language syntax, semantics, and execution environments, allowing developers to focus on language design and implementation without getting bogged down in low-level details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-components-of-truffle-language-implementation-api-lia&quot;&gt;Key Components of Truffle Language Implementation API (LIA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grammar Definition:&lt;/strong&gt; Truffle LIA enables developers to define the syntax and grammar of their custom programming languages using standard notation such as Extended Backus-Naur Form (EBNF). This grammar definition serves as the foundation for parsing and interpreting source code written in the DSL.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parser Generation:&lt;/strong&gt; Truffle LIA includes tools for automatically generating parsers from grammar definitions. These parsers transform input source code into abstract syntax trees (ASTs), which represent the structure and semantics of the code in a hierarchical format.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AST Manipulation:&lt;/strong&gt; Truffle LIA provides APIs and utilities for manipulating ASTs programmatically. Developers can traverse, analyze, and transform ASTs to implement custom language features, perform optimizations, and generate bytecode or intermediate representations for execution on the Ethereum Virtual Machine (EVM).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration with Truffle Suite:&lt;/strong&gt; Truffle LIA seamlessly integrates with other components of the Truffle Suite, such as Truffle Contracts and Truffle Debugger. This integration enables developers to leverage existing tools and workflows for smart contract development while building and testing DSLs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-cases-of-truffle-language-implementation-api-lia&quot;&gt;Use Cases of Truffle Language Implementation API (LIA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Truffle LIA can be applied to various use cases in Ethereum smart contract development, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain-Specific Languages (DSLs):&lt;/strong&gt; Developers can use Truffle LIA to create DSLs tailored to specific application domains, such as finance, supply chain management, or gaming. These DSLs can encapsulate domain-specific logic and constraints, making smart contract development more accessible and intuitive for domain experts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Custom Language Extensions:&lt;/strong&gt; Truffle LIA enables developers to extend existing smart contract languages, such as Solidity or Vyper, with custom syntax and semantics. This capability allows for the creation of high-level abstractions, language features, and domain-specific optimizations to improve developer productivity and code readability.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Language Research:&lt;/strong&gt; Researchers and academics can leverage Truffle LIA to experiment with new programming language concepts and paradigms in the context of Ethereum smart contracts. By prototyping and evaluating custom language designs, researchers can explore novel approaches to contract development and blockchain interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-directions-and-active-development&quot;&gt;Future Directions and Active Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Truffle team continues to enhance and expand the capabilities of the Language Implementation API, incorporating feedback from the developer community and addressing emerging needs and trends in smart contract development. Future updates may include support for additional language features, improved tooling integration, and optimizations for performance and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the Truffle Language Implementation API (LIA) empowers developers to build custom programming languages for Ethereum smart contract development with ease and flexibility. By providing a robust framework for language design, parsing, and execution, Truffle LIA enables innovation and experimentation in blockchain-based application development, driving the evolution of decentralized ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 06:00:01 +0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/cstheory/2021/05/05/the-gayeebi-lang.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sheikhimtiaz.me/cstheory/2021/05/05/the-gayeebi-lang.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cstheory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding Smart Contracts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the realm of blockchain technology, smart contracts have emerged as a revolutionary concept, promising to reshape traditional agreements and transactions. In this comprehensive guide, we delve into what smart contracts are, how to write them, where to deploy them, and explore their diverse use cases across various industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-smart-contract&quot;&gt;What is a Smart Contract?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, a smart contract is a self-executing contract with the terms of the agreement directly written into code. These contracts run on a blockchain network and automatically enforce the terms of the agreement without the need for intermediaries. The immutable nature of blockchain ensures that once deployed, the contract’s code cannot be altered, providing security and transparency to all parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-write-smart-contracts&quot;&gt;How to Write Smart Contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing smart contracts typically involves programming in languages specifically designed for blockchain development, such as Solidity for Ethereum. Developers define the conditions and actions of the contract, including triggers for execution and instructions for handling various scenarios. Smart contracts must be rigorously tested to ensure their functionality and security before deployment on the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-writing-a-simple-smart-contract-in-solidity&quot;&gt;Example: Writing a Simple Smart Contract in Solidity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pragma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;solidity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;SimpleSmartContract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Define a state variable to store a message&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Function to set the message&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setMessage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Function to get the message&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;getMessage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;view&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, we create a simple smart contract using Solidity. The contract allows users to set and get a message stored on the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-deploy-smart-contracts&quot;&gt;Where to Deploy Smart Contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart contracts are deployed on blockchain networks, with Ethereum being one of the most popular platforms for their implementation. Ethereum’s decentralized platform allows developers to deploy smart contracts on its blockchain, enabling global access and execution. Other blockchain platforms, such as Binance Smart Chain and Cardano, also support smart contracts, each offering unique features and capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-cases-of-smart-contracts&quot;&gt;Use Cases of Smart Contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential applications of smart contracts are vast and varied, spanning across numerous industries. Here are some prominent use cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance and Banking: Smart contracts can automate processes such as loan issuance, insurance claims, and decentralized finance (DeFi) protocols, enabling faster and more efficient transactions while reducing the need for intermediaries.
Supply Chain Management: By recording every step of a product’s journey on a blockchain, smart contracts enhance transparency and traceability, reducing fraud and ensuring product authenticity.
Real Estate: Smart contracts can streamline property transactions by automating tasks such as title transfers, escrow agreements, and rental payments, eliminating the need for traditional intermediaries like real estate agents and lawyers.
Healthcare: In healthcare, smart contracts can facilitate secure and transparent sharing of patient data among healthcare providers while ensuring compliance with privacy regulations.
Legal Industry: Smart contracts have the potential to revolutionize the legal industry by automating contract execution, dispute resolution, and intellectual property rights management.
Gaming and Entertainment: Smart contracts can power decentralized gaming platforms, enabling transparent and secure in-game transactions, digital asset ownership, and provably fair gaming experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, smart contracts represent a paradigm shift in the way agreements and transactions are executed, offering efficiency, security, and transparency in various sectors. By understanding the fundamentals of smart contracts, mastering their development, and exploring their diverse use cases, individuals and businesses can harness the full potential of blockchain technology to innovate and transform industries.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 06:00:01 +0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/engineering/2021/04/29/smart-contracts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sheikhimtiaz.me/engineering/2021/04/29/smart-contracts.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>engineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Would it help!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is some discrete thoughts of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, we can divide our world into two or more separate distinct segments. Each segment is another different would to us. We create, simulate and emulate this world for a reason. Each world is valuable to us. We make sure that the components of one world do not collide or intersect with another. We can, but do not create more worlds because we have to take responsibilities for these worlds, every incidents happening in each world and how they co-operate. My family is my first and most important world for me like the most of us. Its my only comfort zone despite the fact that my father thinks of me as an academic failure. My family raised me and fueled me up for better living. But this world is running out of fuels. So, I create new worlds, one after another. Until I find a suitable world to gain energy from and fuel up my primitive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this worlds are ready for me but they are not quite decorated in a order I need. So I panic! And then I wonder a little too. It took some time to get me actually thinking of the problem. A well defined problem is seventy percent solved. So I spend most of the time finding the solution rather than accepting and following a random solution. I reason. And that’s the thing I am talking about. Solutions don’t come easy. Somewhere in between facing the problem and having an actual solution of the problem, I face serious level depression about my capability, my surroundings and available resources. I am only desperate when I am insecure about my job. So I try to convince myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must do my part and things will come through. There is a plan in everything. It all adds up in the end. And even if does not, would it help worrying?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eat. I pray. I work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live a peaceful life. I stay motivated. I hang out with friends time to time. This is my life and its ending one moment at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading me out. I wish everyone finds a moment to enjoy what they have in life and work for a better tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 06:00:01 +0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/reflections/2017/10/20/would-it-help.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sheikhimtiaz.me/reflections/2017/10/20/would-it-help.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>“কিছু কথা” যোগীপাড়াবাসীর</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;বন্ধুসমাজের মন রক্ষা করিতে গিয়া মেস ছাড়িব ঠিক করিলাম বটে, কিন্তু কথা পাকাপোক্ত করিবার পরপরই মন উতলা হইয়া উঠিলো। নতুন করিয়া হিসাব নিকাষ কষিয়া দেখিলাম, নতুন মেসে যাইবার পিছনে বিবিধ কারণ থাকিলেও, পুরাতন মেসখানি ছাড়িবার পিছনে ছটা কারণও নাই। নতুন মেসের সব গুনাবলি লিস্টি করিতে যাইয়া নতুন মেসের একটা গুরুতর দোষ বাহির হইলো। তাহা হইলো যে, সে আমার পুরাতন মেস নয়। বাচ্চু কাকার কথা ভুল প্রমাণ করিয়া দিয়া দেশ আবেগ দিয়া ভাসায় দিলাম। এটা আমার দ্বিতীয়ঘর, প্রথম মেস – ইহাকে ছাড়িয়া আমি কেমন করিয়া থাকিবো?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;মেইনরোড থেকে একটা সোজা গলি গিয়া পরিয়াছে পুরাতন মেসের প্রধান ফটকের সামনে, গলির দুপাশে বিশ্ববিদ্যালয়ের কামলাখাটা মানুষজনের বসতি। কেউ টঙ্গের দোকানে কাজ করিয়া থাকে, অথবা কেও ডি বিল্ডিঙ্গের নাইটগার্ড। সকালে আমি যখন নাস্তা করিতে বের হই, তখন তারা বাড়ি ফেরে। তাদের সাথে একদিন কথায় কথায় শুনিয়াছিলাম শাহরিয়ার ভাইয়ের গল্প – ভাই সারারাত কাজ করিয়া সকালে নাস্তা করিতে যাইতেন টঙ্গের দোকানে। ভালো মানুষ ছিলেন শাহরিয়ার ভাই, তাদের মুখে এই কথা শুনিয়া ভালো লাগিয়াছিলো। তো মেস ছাড়িবার এই লগ্নে আসিরা হটাথ করিয়া খালার অতিরিক্ত পেয়াজ দেয়া চাউমেইন ও সুস্বাদু লাগিলো। বাড়িওয়ালা আন্টির রান্না এম্নিতেই ভালো, সামনের রোজায় তার ইফতারির খুব অভাব বোধ হইবে। এগারোটাকার মারলবোরোটায় মাত্র ধরায় একটা টান দেয়া হইসে, এমন সময় দেখি আঙ্কেল এ বিল্ডিং এর দিক হইতে হন্তদন্ত হইয়া যাত্রীছাউনির দিকে ছুটিয়া আসিতেসেন। ঘর হইতে আরাইশো কিলো দূরে আসিয়াও যে কাউকে দেখিয়া সিগারেট ফালাই দিতে হবে সেই চিন্তা একদম মাথায় ছিলো না।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;সিলেটে আমার পরিবার বলতে এই মেসটাই যা ছিলো। পরিবারের সবাইকে কথাটা কিভাবে জানাবো তা ঠিক করার আগেই তাহাদের থেকে প্রস্তাব পাইলাম, তাহারা তাদের ডিপার্টমেন্টের মানুষ ঠিক করিয়াছে আমার সিটে তোলার জন্য। আমার চলে যাওয়ার ব্যাপারে তাদেরকে খুব একটা বিচলিত মনে হইলো না। এতে আমারই সুবিধা, চলে যাওয়াটা সহজ হবে, কিন্তু অযথাই আমার রক্ত গরম হইলো। শুয়ারের বাচ্চাগুলার তলপেটে লাত্থি মারার প্রবল ইচ্ছাকে সংবরন করিয়া  লইলাম। এইখানে প্রসঙ্গত উল্লেখ যে, আমাদের মেস এখন আর ফ্ল্যাট সিস্টেমের নাই। অর্থাৎ আগে আমরা মেসে কয়জন থাকি তা গুরুত্বপূর্ণ ছিলো না, মাসশেষে আঙ্কেল্কে বুঝে বুঝে দশহাজার টাকা দিয়ে দিতে হত। আঙ্কেল একদিন ঠিক করিলো কে যায় কে থাকে ব্যাপার না, আমাদের এখন থেকে আমাদের সিটের ভাড়া দিলেই চলবে। মনুষ্য প্রজাতির কাছ থেকে আমার প্রত্যাশা অনেক কম, তবুও এরকম একটা মুহূর্তে দ্বিতীয় পরিবারের এহেন ব্যবহারে খুবই ব্যাথিত হইলাম।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;যাই হোক, মেসে গবাদি পশু ব্যাতিরেকে আরো কিছু জিনিস ছিলো অভাব বোধ করিবার মত। অনেকদিন মেসের ছাদে উঠা হয়না। কলের পান্থ কানাই এর কথা খুব মনে ধরিয়াছিলো। সামনের মাসে একটা গিটার কিনিয়া এই ছাদে বসিয়া টুংটাং করিবার কথা ছিলো। কিন্তু সেই কথা ধরিয়া বসিয়া থাকিলে হইবেক না। অইদিকে শিরোনামহীন বলেছে, “কিছু কথা কখনো হারিয়ে যায়”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;দ্বিতীয় বর্ষের চূড়ান্ত পরিক্ষার বাহানা দিয়া দফা কিছুটা পিছানো গেলো। তবে সেই লগ্ন ক্রমশই নিকট হইয়া আসিতেছে। আসুক, দিনে দিনে সময় কম হয় নাই।&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 06:00:01 +0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://sheikhimtiaz.me/reflections/2016/08/27/jogi-para-mess.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sheikhimtiaz.me/reflections/2016/08/27/jogi-para-mess.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
